Finding Aid for the Holland Nimmons McTyeire Sermons
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
Holland Nimmons McTyeire Sermons
1844-1850
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0282
.42 linear_feet
This collection of 163 of Bishop McTyeire’s early sermons came to the library about 1957 from John J. Tigert IV. They had been sent to his father, John J. Tigert III by J. D. Hamilton in 1894 after they were discovered, along with some papers of Bishop Soule, “in the stable at Bp. McTyeire’s by Nellie the cook” (see letter in folder 36).
Most of the sermons were preached to the Methodist congregations to which McTyeire was minister; a few were preached to other groups such as Negroes and sailors; one was preached on board a riverboat. Many are annotated by McTyeire, retrospectively and informally; he includes his own criticism (based on hindsight), comments by others, remarks on the circumstances under which the sermon was preached, and other incidental comments of an autobiographical nature* There are also some handwritten annotations, as to date, location, etc., by John j. Tigert III and John J. Tigert IV.
Following is a key to where the sermons were preached:
1 - 29. Williamsburg, Va., and elsewhere in Virginia, 1844-1846.
30 - 61. Mobile, Ala., 1846-1847.
62 - 96. Demopolis, Ala., and vicinity, 1847.
97 - 107. Flynn and McTyeire Course of Lectures, Demopolis, Ala., 1847.
108 - 115. Columbus, Miss., and vicinity, 1848.
116 - 163. New Orleans, La., 1849-1850.
- “Coming of the Kingdom,”, March 1844 (Box 1, Item 1)
- “Confessing before Men,”, April 13, 1844 (Box 1, Item 2)
- “Besetting Sins,”, May 4, 1844 (Box 1, Item 3)
- “Be Not Deceived,”, May 6, 1844 (Box 1, Item 4)
- “Quench Not the Spirit,”, Sept. 14, 1844 (Box 1, Item 5)
- “Watch and Pray,”, Jan. 26, 1845 (Box 1, Item 6)
- “Restore unto me the joy of the salvation 6c uphold me with thy &c,”, 1845 (Box 1, Item 7)
- “John the Baptist,”, March 28, 1845 (Box 1, Item 8)
- “The Fruits of Sin,”, Dec. 6, 1845 (Box 1, Item 9)
- “God’s Witnesses,”, Dec. 9, 1845 (Box 1, Item 10)
- “Free Indeed,”, 1845 (Box 1, Item 11)
- “The Fruits of Holiness,”, Dec. 21, 1845 (Box 1, Item 12)
- “Mercy vs. Judgement,”, 1845 (Box 1, Item 13)
- “The Choice of Moses,”, 1845 (Box 1, Item 14)
- “Redeeming Time,”, Jan. 4, 1846 (Box 1, Item 15)
- “My First Text,”, Jan. 12, 1846 (Box 1, Item 16)
- “Your Bodies, Temples,”, Jan. 22, 1846 (Box 1, Item 17)
- “A Change of Heart,”, Feb. 1, 1846 (Box 1, Item 18)
- “Reaping What Is Sowed,”, Feb. 8, 1846 (Box 1, Item 19)
- “Walking Surely,”, Feb. 15, 1846 (Box 1, Item 20)
- “Providence,”, Feb. 22, 1846 (Box 1, Item 21)
- “The Single Eye,”, March 19, 1846 (Box 1, Item 22)
- “The Devils and Angels,”, March 22, 1846 (Box 1, Item 23)
- “Slow to Anger,”, March 30, 1846 (Box 1, Item 24)
- “The New Creature,”, March 30, 1846 (Box 1, Item 25)
- “Drinking into One Spirit,”, Apr. 5, 1846 (Box 1, Item 26)
- “The Love of Our Neighbors,”, Apr. 28, 1846 (Box 1, Item 27)
- “Sermon on Taking Charge of the Congregation,”, Nov. 30, 1846 (Box 1, Item 28)
- “God’s Goodness Leads to Repentance,”, July 25, 1847 (Box 1, Item 29)
- “The Man of God Who Went from Bethel,”, 1846 (Box 1, Item 30)
- “Love of God (objectively),”, June 1846 (Box 1, Item 31)
- “A Goodly Heritage,”, 1846 (Box 1, Item 32)
- “Wrath Revealed,”, July 1, 1846 (Box 1, Item 33)
- “Spiritual Adultery,”, July 9, 1846 (Box 1, Item 34)
- “The First Adam vs. Second Adam”, July 21, 1846 (Box 1, Item 35)
- “About Jonah,”, July 24, 1846 (Box 1, Item 36)
- “A Door Keeper’s Place,”, July 26, 1846 (Box 1, Item 37)
- “The Offense and the Free Gift,”, August 1, 1846 (Box 1, Item 38)
- “Walking by Faith,”, August 8, 1846 (Box 1, Item 39)
- “Follow Me as I Follow Christ,”, August 20, 1846 (Box 1, Item 40)
- “The Wedding Garment,”, Sept. 8, 1846 (Box 1, Item 41)
- “All Men Are Liars (The Unjust Accusation),”, Sept. 12, 1846 (Box 1, Item 42)
- “The Short Bed,”, Sept. 27, 1846 (Box 1, Item 43)
- “Full of Grace and Truth,”, Oct. 16, 1846 (Box 1, Item 44)
- “Not Every One,”, Oct. 26, 1846 (Box 1, Item 45)
- “Our Father Which Art in Heaven,”, Oct. 29, 1846 (Box 1, Item 46)
- “And Forgive Us Our Debts, as We Forgive Our Debtors,”, Nov. 1846 (Box 1, Item 47)
- “Thanksgiving Day,”, Nov. 5, 1846 (Box 1, Item 48)
- “The Proud Heart, an Abomination,”, Nov. 7, 1846 (Box 1, Item 49)
- “Pray for the Peace of Jerusalem,”, Nov. 8, 1846 (Box 1, Item 50)
- “A little that a righteous man hath is better than the riches of many wicked,”, Nov. 15, 1846 (Box 1, Item 51)
- “God Performing His Work in Us,”, Nov. 15, 1846 (Box 1, Item 52)
- “Remember the Sabbath Day to Keep It Holy,“, Nov. 20, 1846 (Box 1, Item 53)
- “Sailor Sermon,”, Nov. 30, 1846 (Box 1, Item 54)
- “At Ease in Zion,”, Dec. 6, 1846 (Box 1, Item 55)
- “Remember the Sabbath day to keep it holy,”, Dec. 6, 1846 (Box 1, Item 56)
- “Inheritance of Saints,”, Dec. 10, 1846 (Box 1, Item 57)
- “Love,”, Dec. 18, 1846 (Box 1, Item 58)
- “The Sower and Seed,”, Dec. 27, 1846 (Box 1, Item 59)
- “The Indian’s Sermon,”, Jan. 17, 1847 (Box 1, Item 60)
- Speech at a Temperance Meeting, 1847 (Box 1, Item 61)
- Subjects for sermons during this summer’s campaign, 1847 (Box 1, Item 62)
- “Life More Abundantly,”, March 20, 1847 (Box 1, Item 63)
- “The Perishing Meat,”, March 21, 1847 (Box 1, Item 64)
- “Deny Thyself,”, March 26, 1847 (Box 1, Item 65)
- “Take up Thy Cross and Follow Me,”, March 27, 1847 (Box 1, Item 66)
- “Secret Faults,”, April 1, 1847 (Box 1, Item 67)
- “The Backslider in Heart,”, April 4, 1847 (Box 1, Item 68)
- “Stop That Thought!!!,”, April 9, 1847 (Box 1, Item 69)
- “In the Woods,”, April 15, 1847 (Box 1, Item 70)
- “Signs Following the Word,”, April 30, 1847 (Box 1, Item 71)
- “Leaven of Pharisees,”, May 2, 1847 (Box 1, Item 72)
- “Pulling Down - Destroying,”, May 8, 1847 (Box 1, Item 73)
- “Building Up,”, May 12, 1847 (Box 1, Item 74)
- “The Citizen of Zion,”, May 22, 1847 (Box 1, Item 75)
- “Godly Sorrow,”, June 1, 1847 (Box 1, Item 76)
- “God’s Peace Gift,”, June 6, 1847 (Box 1, Item 77)
- “Secret Faults,”, June 25, 1847 (Box 1, Item 78)
- “Forgetting God,”, July 18, 1847 (Box 1, Item 79)
- “Wretchedness of the Sinner,”, July 30, 1847 (Box 1, Item 80)
- “Grace,”, August 1, 1847 (Box 1, Item 81)
- “Parable of the Talents,”, August 22, 1847 (Box 1, Item 82)
- “God in Christ, Reconciling,”, Sept. 4, 1847 (Box 1, Item 83)
- “Infant Salvation,”, Sept. 12, 1847 (Box 1, Item 84)
- “The Affair of Aeham,”, Sept. 25, 1847 (Box 1, Item 85)
- “Solicitude for Souls,”, Sept. 27, 1847 (Box 1, Item 86)
- “The Negative Part of a Blessed Character,”, Oct. 3, 1847 (Box 1, Item 87)
- Funeral occasion: Mrs. Perkins, Oct. 3, 1847 (Box 1, Item 88)
- “Almost Persuaded,”, Oct. 16, 1847 (Box 1, Item 89)
- “The Evergreen Christian,”, Oct. 31, 1847 (Box 1, Item 90)
- “Worship God,”, Nov. 27, 1847 (Box 1, Item 91)
- “The Security of a Good Man,”, Nov. 27, 1847 (Box 1, Item 92)
- “The Praise of Men and Praise of God,”, Dec. 5, 1847 (Box 1, Item 93)
- “The Heirs of Salvation,”, Dec. 19, 1847 (Box 1, Item 94)
- “Temptation of Christ,”, 1847 (Box 1, Item 95)
- “How can ye escape the damnation of hell?”, Fall, 1847 (Box 1, Item 96)
- Lecture 1, “The Existence of God,”, April 22, 1847 (Box 1, Item 97)
- Lecture 3, “Spirituality of the Divine Nature,”, May 6, 1847 (Box 1, Item 98)
- Lecture 4, “Goodness of God,”, June 4, 1847 (Box 1, Item 99)
- Lecture 5, “Ye Do Err, Not Knowing the Power of God,”, May 20, 1847 (Box 1, Item 100)
- Lecture 6, “Sub love Semper Eris,”, May 27, 1847 (Box 1, Item 101)
- Lecture 7, “Holiness of God,” n.d (Box 1, Item 102)
- Lecture 8, “Of Revealed Religion,”, August 19, 1847 (Box 1, Item 103)
- Lecture 9, “Authenticity of the Holy Scriptures,”, Sept. 8, 1847 (Box 1, Item 104)
- Lecture 10, “Miracles,”, Sept. 23, 1847 (Box 1, Item 105)
- Lecture 11, “Prophecy,”, Sept. 29, 1847 (Box 1, Item 106)
- Lecture 12, “Rule of Faith,”, Dec. 3, 1847 (Box 1, Item 107)
- “Notes on Mohammedism,”, May 9, 1848 (Box 1, Item 108)
- “Out of Seeming Evil - Still Educing Good,”, Feb. 29, 1848 (Box 1, Item 109)
- “The Temptation,”, May 1848 (Box 1, Item 110)
- “Second Sermon on the Temptation,”, June 1848 (Box 1, Item 111)
- “Love,”, July 22, 1848 (Box 1, Item 112)
- “The Daily Death to Sin,”, Oct. 7, 1848 (Box 1, Item 113)
- “Avenging Ourselves,”, 1848 (Box 1, Item 114)
- “Agur’s Prayer,”, Oct. 1848 (Box 1, Item 115)
- “Destroying the Works of the Devil,” n.d (Box 1, Item 116)
- “Thoughts about Prayer Meeting,”, March 22, 1849 (Box 1, Item 117)
- “Returning,”, April 8, 1849 (Box 1, Item 118)
- “A Lively Concern for the Salvation of Souls.. .,”, June 15, 1849 (Box 1, Item 119)
- “Enmity of the Carnal Mind,”, July 1, 1849 (Box 1, Item 120)
- “Death Will Benight You,”, July 3, 1849 (Box 1, Item 121)
- “Jesus made a sin-offering for us, who knew no sin,”, July 15, 1849 (Box 1, Item 122)
- “Keeping the Passover,”, July 31, 1849 (Box 1, Item 123)
- “National Fast Day,”, August 3, 1849 (Box 1, Item 124)
- “The True Grounds of Condemnation—Neglect of Salvation,”, August 5, 1849 (Box 1, Item 125)
- “Spiritual Temperance and Intemperance,”, August 12, 1849 (Box 1, Item 126)
- “The Claims of the Flesh,”, August 14, 1849 (Box 1, Item 127)
- “The Captive Maid,”, August 17, 1849 (Box 1, Item 128)
- “Entering into Covenant,” New Orleans, August 19, 1849 (Box 1, Item 129)
- “Holy Living among the Unholy,”, August 26, 1849 (Box 1, Item 130)
- “The Work of God,”, Sept. 2, 1849 (Box 1, Item 131)
- “To Overcome the World,”, Sept. 10, 1849 (Box 1, Item 132)
- “The Better Offering,”, Sept. 17, 1849 (Box 1, Item 133)
- “Jabez’s Prayer,”, Sept. 21, 1849 (Box 1, Item 134)
- “The Mustard Seed,”, Oct. 1, 1849 (Box 1, Item 135)
- “Living to Die,”, Oct. 11, 1849 (Box 1, Item 136)
- “Unprofitable Servants, After All,”, Oct. 26, 1849 (Box 1, Item 137)
- “The Nine Reasons,”, Nov. 4, 1849 (Box 1, Item 138)
- “A Converted Nobleman,”, Jan. 12, 1850 (Box 1, Item 139)
- “The Poor Spirit,”, March 17, 1950 (Box 1, Item 140)
- “Chastenings,”, March 31, 1850 (Box 1, Item 141)
- “Partakers of the Divine Nature,”, April 20, 1850 (Box 1, Item 142)
- “Christian Resignation,”, April 28, 1850 (Box 1, Item 143)
- “The Proclamation,”, May 10, 1850 (Box 1, Item 144)
- “Sheba and the Wise Woman,”, June 2, 1850 (Box 1, Item 145)
- “Are you sure you are willing? Bo you consent to be holy? Can you?”, June 9, 1950 (Box 1, Item 146)
- “The Tabernacle Put Off and the House Put On,”, June 23, 1850 (Box 1, Item 147)
- “Like Little Children,”, June 30, 1850 (Box 1, Item 148)
- “Covenanting by Sacrifice,”, July 7, 1850 (Box 1, Item 149)
- “Parable of the Talents,”, July 15, 1850 (Box 1, Item 150)
- “Walking in the Truth,”, July 21, 1850 (Box 1, Item 151)
- “Three Sermons,”, August 4, 1850 (Box 1, Item 152)
- “A Jealous God,”, August 17, 1850 (Box 1, Item 153)
- “If Our Heart Condemn Us,”, Sept. 1, 1850 (Box 1, Item 154)
- “The Redeemer’s Distinct Care and Watchfulness over the Church — the Letter to Ephesus,”, Sept. 28, 1850 (Box 1, Item 155)
- “The Middle State: or State of the Dead,”, Sept. 28, 1850 (Box 1, Item 156)
- “Christ, a High Priest,”, Oct. 3, 1850 (Box 1, Item 157)
- “Grace Received in Vain,”, Oct. 12, 1850 (Box 1, Item 158)
- “The Temptation in the Wilderness,”, Oct. 20, 1850 (Box 1, Item 159)
- “Things Seen vs. Things Not Seen,”, Oct. 25, 1850 (Box 1, Item 160)
- “The Tower, Unfinished,”, Nov. 17, 1850 (Box 1, Item 161)
- “Quickening,”, Nov. 24, 1850 (Box 1, Item 162)
- “The Kingdom of God,”, Dec. 8, 1850 (Box 1, Item 163)